In this video, we're going to look at
how to train a ref mod for Miniax H3.
To accomplish this, we will need two
custom nodes and one optional node. Open
a terminal where you have Comfy UI
installed. Then change directories into
the custom nodes folder.
Next, we will click on the green code
button and copy the URL.
Now we will use the command getit clone
and paste the URL to clone the
repository into our custom nodes folder.
I have already installed these nodes so
that is why it displays an error saying
it already exists.
And now we will do the exact same thing
with the second node. Click the green
code button, copy the URL, then use the
get clone command in the terminal.
The final node is optional, but it will
speed up generation times. If you do
want to install it, just follow the
exact same steps as the previous node.
Again, I already have it installed, so
that is why this message is displayed.
Now, start Comfy UI and open up a blank
workflow.
Now, in Comfy UI, double click anywhere
on the canvas and search for create H3
ref from folder.
As you can see, we will need a video and
audio VAE.
Just search for the load VAE node and
select the Minimax H3 VAE.
Now place another load VAE node so we
can load the Minimax audio VAE
and connect the respective VAE nodes to
the inputs of the ref mod node.
I figured the best way to demonstrate
this was to create a ref mod of myself.
One, because I am not in the base
Minimax training data, and two, because
I control the rights to my image. So, I
collected images of myself. You will
just want to place the images into a
folder. No captioning is needed. You can
also provide videos, but in the interest
of time, I am only using images for now.
From my understanding, you can do audio
as well. Then, in the refod node in the
folder field, you provide it with the
path to your collection of images. If
you have subfolders containing images,
then click use subfolders. Since I have
just a single folder, I will leave it
unchecked.
In the use folder as name field, I will
uncheck it since my folder is named
test. To make things easy, I will just
place my name in this field.
And then for the extraction preset,
since I am creating a ref mod of myself,
I will leave it at identity and code.
But you can also create ref mods based
on styles or motion.
And finally, make sure you have the save
field enabled. So it will save the
generated save tensors file after we run
it. And now I will run the ref mod node.
And as we can see, it generated our
RefMod file using 24 images in only 5
and 1/2 seconds.
Now, let's look at how to actually use
the file.
Here we have a workflow, which don't
worry, I will link it in the description
so you don't have to recreate it. Uh,
essentially you will want all of the
typical nodes when using Miniax H3, the
video and audio VAE and the clip.
I will be using the MiniAX H3 reference
to video in 8 version, but from my
testing, this will work with other
fine-tunes.
And in the load H3 refs node, we can
select our refod file. The node creator
also provided an example file. You can
also combine multiple ref mods, such as
in the mod 2 field, but for now, we will
only be using one. For our prompt, the
general Minimax H3 prompting guide works
well. The creator of the Minax H3 mod
nodes also has a much more in-depth
guide on how to prompt. In this case, we
are just going with a simple prompt.
While this is running, I thought it
would be good to actually describe the
difference between a Ref mod and Allora.
Allora works by training on a set of
images or videos and learning small
changes to the model's weights. Those
learn changes are saved into a
lightweight file that can later be
applied to recreate a character style or
concept. A ref mod takes a different
approach. Instead of training the model,
it runs your reference images or videos
through Miniax H3's VAE and converts
them into latent representations. Those
reference latent are then saved into a
small file that can be reused during
generation. That also makes ref mods
dramatically faster to create. Training
Allora can take hours depending on the
data set, hardware, and settings.
Creating a ref mod mostly involves
encoding the references, so it can often
be produced in seconds or minutes
instead. The files can also be much
smaller. A video model can easily be
tens or hundreds of megabytes, while
refs can be only a few megabytes. So,
while teaches the model something new by
modifying its weights, a ref mod
essentially saves a reusable
representation of your references in
H3's latent space. It is faster to
create, much smaller, and doesn't
require a traditional training process.
All right. Now, let's have a look at the
finished video.
>> This is demonstration of the EIE Miniax
H3 ref.
>> So, it gets the identity down well, but
as you can probably tell, it does not
sound like me. However, there are ways
to fix that, such as with an audio ref
mod. It is not a limitation of ref mods,
just beyond the scope of this video. For
comparison, here is a video generated by
a Laura from a separate project I was
working on. How can a file that is only
a few hundred megabytes or sometimes
much smaller teach a multi-billion
parameter AI model an entirely new
character visual style product or
behavior? Ref mods are still a very new
technique and I am sure many
improvements will be made. I still have
a lot to learn about them myself. All
the credit goes to the node authors
shown throughout this video. They
created these techniques. I just saw
people were having trouble with this and
figured a video may help. With that
being said, things move very quickly in
the AI space. So depending on when you
watch this, ref mods may have already
changed or improved, but for now they're
an interesting new option for getting
consistent characters and concepts in
Minimax H3 without the time and
complexity of training Aora.